# Austin Xu

CONTACT Information Phone: (248) 402-3571 Email: axu77@gatech.edu https://austinxu87.github.io/

RESEARCH INTERESTS Interested human preference learning, recommender systems, ranking systems, and learning from non-metric queries. Broadly interested in leveraging the learned representations of foundational models (generative models, large language models, etc.) for learning.

EDUCATION

## Georgia Institute of Technology

Aug. 2019 - May 2024 (expected)

PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Concentration: Digital Signal Processing and Machine Learning

Advisor: Dr. Mark Davenport

GPA: 4.00/4.00

# University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Sept. 2015 - May 2019

BSE in Electrical Engineering, Summa Cum Laude

Concentration: Digital Signal Processing

GPA: 3.98/4.00

Publications

- [5] A. Xu, J. Wang, A. D. McRae, A. Pananjady, M. A. Davenport, "Parametric adjustment queries: A new paradigm for human data elicitation with applications to metric learning," *In preparation*.
- [4] N. Nadagouda, A. Xu, and M. A. Davenport, "Active metric learning and classification using similarity queries, to appear in *Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI)*, Pittsburgh, August 2023. (31% conference acceptance rate)

Short version in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Workshop on Human in the Loop Learning, New Orleans, December 2022.

[3] A. Xu, M. I. Vasileva, A. Dave, A. Seshadri, "HandsOff: Labeled dataset generation with no additional human annotations," to appear in *IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, Vancouver, June 2023. **Highlight Award (top 2.5% of submissions, 26% conference acceptance rate).** 

Short version in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) SyntheticData4ML Workshop, New Orleans, December 2022.

- [2] A. D. McRae, A. Xu, J. Jin, N. Nadagouda, N. Ahad, P. Guan, S. Karnik, M. A. Davenport, "Delta distancing: A lifting approach to localizing items from user comparisons," in *IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing (ICASSP)*, Singapore, May 2022.
- [1] A. Xu and M. A. Davenport, "Simultaneous Preference and Metric Learning from Paired Comparisons," in *Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)*, Online, December 2020. Spotlight Presentation (top 4% of submissions, 20% conference acceptance rate).

Industry Experience **Duolingo**, Pittsburgh, PA AI Research Intern

Incoming, Summer 2023

Amazon, San Francisco, CA

May 2022 - December 2022

Applied Scientist Intern, Amazon Style

- Investigated pixel-wise labeled synthetic dataset generation with generative adversarial networks (GANs). Leveraged GAN inversion to utilize existing labeled images for label generator training. Achieved state-of-the-art performance in faces, cars, full-body humans, urban driving domains on semantic segmentation, keypoint detection, depth estimation tasks.
- Project resulted in the first full conference publication for the Amazon Style organization: Paper accepted at CVPR as a Highlight Award (top 2.5% of submissions, top 10% of accepted papers). Workshop version presented at NeurIPS.

- Developed variance-maximization algorithm for selecting initial items to be shown to users for binary like/dislike ratings (cold start problem). Experimented combinations of CLIP and model embeddings to determine embedding to maximize inter-and intra-category variance.
- Designed and implemented data fidelity experiments which exposed recommendation model embedding shortcomings. Findings handed off to management for review, potentially leading to a massive simplification of training pipeline and user experience.

## Sandia National Laboratories, Albuquerque, NM

May 2018 - Aug. 2018

Undergraduate R&D Intern, Flight and Instrumentation Systems Group

#### General Motors, Warren, MI

May 2017 - Aug. 2017

Student Intern, Automated Driving and Active Safety Group

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Advisor: Mark Davenport

Learning from parametric adjustment queries.

2021 - present

• Investigating robust metric learning under non-parametric human noise models from novel parametric adjustment queries. Developing sample complexity guarantees using techniques from high-dimensional statistics and low-rank matrix sensing.

Deep metric learning from nearest-neighbor queries.

2020 - 2022

- Developed information-theoretic criterion for adaptive selection of a novel nearest neighbor query. Query responses directly improve learned embeddings, allowing for direct application of adaptive query selection to both active deep metric learning (DML) and active classification.
- Implemented DML experiments (python) which outperformed recent active DML approaches on synthetic and real-world datasets (food-100, Georgia Tech graduate student admissions).

Simultaneous preference and metric learning from paired comparisons.

2019 - 2020

- Developed novel joint ideal point and Mahalanobis metric estimation algorithm from paired comparisons. Utilized alternating minimization to iteratively refine initial estimates.
- Implemented ideal point estimation on synthetic and real-world datasets (Georgia Tech graduate student admissions), resulting in interpretable learned metrics and ideal points.

# University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Advisor: Laura Balzano

- Investigated use of order-weighted L1 (OWL) norm for determining relevant features for learning human preferences from paired comparisons. Characterized effects parameter tuning for OWL norm for promoting group sparsity.
- Developed algorithm to perform blind sensor calibration for data drawn from time-varying low-rank subspaces. Alternated sensor gain learning via Total Least Squares and subspace estimation via GROUSE. Achieved < 5% sensor calibration error with good initialization.

#### Presentations

"HandsOff: Labeled dataset generation with no additional human annotation." May 2023 ML Collective Deep Learning: Classics and Trends reading group | Virtual.

"HandsOff: Labeled dataset generation with no additional human annotation." April 2023 Georgia Tech Center for Signal and Information Processing (CSIP) Seminar | Atlanta, GA.

"HandsOff: Labeled dataset generation with no additional human annotation." December Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) SyntheticData4ML Workshop | New Orleans, LA.

"Simultaneous Preference and Metric Learning from Paired Comparisons." Dec. 2020 Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Spotlight Presentation | Virtual.

Gene Golub SIAM Summer School: "Theory and Practice of Deep Learning." African Institute for Mathematical Sciences (AIMS) | Virtual.

2021

Workshops

Teaching Experience	Head Graduate Teaching Assistant Statistical Machine Learning (ECE 6254)   Georgia Institute of Technology.	Spring 2022	
EXPERIENCE	Statistical Machine Learning (ECE 6254)   Georgia Institute of Technology.		
	Graduate Teaching Assistant Fall 2019	Fall 2019 - Summer 2020	
	Professional and Technical Communications (ECE 3005)   Georgia Institute of Technology.		
	Instructional Aide Fall 20	Fall 2018, Winter 2019	
	Discrete Mathematics (EECS 203)   University of Michigan.		
AWARDS	Machine Learning at Georgia Tech Fellow   Georgia Institute of Technology.	2021	
	President's Fellowship   Georgia Institute of Technology.	2019	
	Distinguished Academic Achievement Award   University of Michigan.	2019	
	Outstanding Service Award, EECS Dept.   University of Michigan.	2018	
	EECS Scholar   University of Michigan.	2018	
	Eta Kappa Nu Scholarship   University of Michigan.	2017	
	UROP Outstanding Research Presentation Award   University of Michigan.	2017	
	James B. Angell Scholar   University of Michigan.	2017	
	William J. Branstrom Freshman Prize   University of Michigan.	2016	
	Dean's List/University Honors   University of Michigan.	2015 - 2019	
SERVICE	Undergraduate Engineering Student Advisory Board	2018 - 2019	
	Electrical Engineering Representative   University of Michigan.		
	Eta Kappa Nu - Beta Epsilon Chapter	2018	
	Officer - Historian, Tutoring Chair   University of Michigan.		
	ECE Undergraduate Advising Office	2017 - 2018	
	Peer Advisor   University of Michigan.		